For those of you who work in the city,
is there anything that you would love
for those in the BBS to know that that
they don't realize about uh about what
you do? Uh any misconceptions, anything
like that? Go ahead and have at it.
>> Church growth in the city is probably uh
five times less than church growth in
the suburbs.
How's that one? [clears throat]
>> In other words, you're saying that's a
misconception. Yeah. I mean, you know,
in in in the city, I think it's just a
much like like I think probably most of
the guys on this call, if they were
planting a church in the suburbs, uh
they'd be at 250 way before they'd be at
250 in the city. That's my that's my
experience.
>> Very good.
>> Not just in my own work, but I mean in
in other guys that come into the city to
do a work. So it's a completely
different,
you know, concept uh for people um to
think where after x amount of time where
you should be numbers wise.
>> Yeah. Daniel, why do you think that is?
Why do why do you think it it's slower?
Well, I I think uh a lot of the reasons
that people are in the city, whether
it's uh number one, like where we were
in Detroit or where we are in Detroit,
it's like young professionals moving
into the city because they think it'll
be cool or people living in section 8
housing in and on government assistance.
Uh both of those the the people moving
into the city, the young professional
faith and religion is one of the last
things on their mind. the reason they're
there is a whole bunch of other reasons.
And then the people, the poor people
that are in the city, it's one of the
last things on their mind because
they're just trying to figure out where
they're going to sleep tonight and what
they're going to eat. So you got two
people groups really that don't lend
themselves much to church growth.
>> Dan, how does that shape how you manage
your collegial model?
um have breakfast with a homeless person
and dinner with a billionaire. I mean,
>> it's just it's really,
you know, really, you just have to be
able to
uh meet and speak with every spectrum of
people group and and then you just go
where God leads you and where there's an
open door, whether it's with the poor or
whether it's with somebody that's going
to help you fund the thing, you just go
there.
>> Good stuff. Jeeoff, you were getting
ready to say something.
>> [clears throat]
>> Yeah, I was just going to talk about
sort of the at least potentially the
misconception that uh and this was maybe
coming back from the 80s when people
would say, "Oh, well, this the city's a
you know, it's a dark place." And I
think the city's a glorious place and I
think most of us who minister in urban
areas think it's a glorious place. Um
that yeah, you actually see harsher
things than probably see elsewhere
because they aren't hidden here. uh but
there's so many glories that are brought
out in the city as well. So uh I think
most of us you know there's there's
definitely difficulties there's
inconveniences
of ministering in the city. Um but there
it's a glorious place to minister and
that's like the one misconception I
would perhaps like address.
[clears throat]
>> Good word. And I think um if I could
just interject um there is a
depth to the re relationship in the city
that
my wife and I as suburbanites have never
experienced before. You know, just
people saying, "Be sure to call me when
you get home so I know you made it
safe." is not an occasional or once in a
while thing. It's every time
>> because people deeply care about each
other. It was probably three or four
years ago when my wife turned to me and
said, "Thank you so much for moving me
into the inner city."
>> And I was
shocked.
>> And I picked my mouth up off the floor
and said, "Why would you say that?" And
she said, "Because I have never had such
deep relationships before in my life."
>> That's beautiful.
>> Yeah. go hand in hand with that and say
part of that is that that privacy is not
a value in the city as much as it is
other places. You you have shared parks,
shared laundromats, shared sidewalks,
shared public spaces that shared life is
part of life in the city that it's
forced. You can't escape it. Um and
that's again kind of what Dan's saying.
That's that's a that's a wonderful thing
that actually adds to the richness of
urban life. I think there's a humility
too that um nobody I don't have to do a
whole lot of work to convince somebody
that they're a sinner.
Everybody is a sinner in the city. And
so we start from our common
identity as sinners
um living our lives before the face of
God. And so that humility as a starting
point leads very easily into grace for
each other, into understanding our need
for each other. and and um and I think
that's another part of the tightness
that that
>> that's kind of what uh Schaefer was
lamenting, you know, 50 years ago with
this thing on personal peace and
affluence and how we don't know our
neighbors in the BBS and uh and you guys
are just speaking into the beauty of
what was left behind.
>> I think I would somebody on the uh on
the street, can I pray for you? and that
person will say yes immediately.
>> I I do that at the mall in the suburbs
and they're offended.
>> I I think that's actually speaks to when
we're talking about city, we're talking
about a big definition here
>> because uh I would say in my context,
people probably think they're more
righteous than they are sinners.
>> And I think if I stopped and said, "Can
I pray for you?" they would run away
fast. Um and so uh you know
demographically
cities have variance themselves
depending on where you are. Um just
speaking personally
um
Jeff
uh reminded me of something in my first
conversation I ever had with Tim Keller.
We came up to visit my wife and I and he
he said uh I guess because he had seen
enough people like burn out or run away.
He just said the city will drain you so
it has to energize you and just what
Jeff was saying the city energizes
uh me but also um the conditions
require a lot of effort to be a calm
presence.
I'd say anxiety feels higher in cities
because of all the reasons we said. And
so I find it takes among our people
a lot of effort just to try not to be
anxious. [clears throat]
>> Fascinating. But you know, Glenn, you
have a very special outlet too, right?
>> Oh. Uh I'm sorry. Music.
>> Oh yeah. No, I I do. that that becomes
uh that's yeah that's that's
a good way to interact with the city in
ways that
>> yeah it's another way for me to see the
city
>> you know maybe this unique to Detroit
but
>> uh one of the things I found and this
this uh goes to Dan's point that we have
found the the same warm-heartedness
in Detroit, but it's because there just
almost is literally nobody that we meet
that's from downtown Detroit.
>> Um, they either are stuck there because
that's where they could get affordable
housing or they moved away from their
families to that spot. They were not
raised there. So, in a sense, it feels
like, you know, it's it's Jerusalem back
in the day the church was founded. where
all these people are thrown in there
>> and there's a better chance that they
can become family and and also to Dan's
point, it's uh uh or maybe it was No, I
think it was Dan. Uh I we could go up to
anybody on the street and say, "Can I
pray for you?" And they'd say, "Please."
>> So just Yeah. different context, Glenn.
Yeah, for sure. [clears throat]
>> Eric, you were getting ready to say
something.
>> Yeah. Um, and yeah, I think a couple
things we're touching on that are
important is what does city mean
anymore? Uh, so I think depending on
where you are, you know, things are
changing rapidly. Um, so those words and
what does urban mean? What does inner
city mean? What does the city at large
mean? I think those are just certain
things. I don't know if those are
misconceptions, but I think they all
sort of conjure up something in our mind
and they might be different. Um, and so
I find sometimes just even the
definitions of words, we're not even
talking about the same thing.
>> Um, and then you got places like I mean
I'm in the south, I think [snorts] I'm
the only one, right? So, but you got
place like Atlanta where I mean what was
the inner city is now, you know,
million-dollar homes and, you know, New
York's done the same thing in all the
places in certain ways. But, but that
really does change things. It really
there's a there's a different reality of
where people are and those types of
things. So, that's a thing. Um, second
thing I'd say, if it's a misconception,
but it's certainly something to
understand is I remember when we stopped
having our worship service. Um, and
that's a whole story, but I remember
people coming to me and saying, "Well,
gosh, what are you going to do now?" And
I said the very same thing I've been
doing for the past however long because
the worship service is a moment in our
week, but when you're in this city,
ministry never stops. um in a certain in
a maybe a different type of way where I
think in the suburbs or whatever you're
you're sort of the week is this time of
preparation it seems like you know for a
thing that happens you know on Sunday
and and and all the things that are
happening maybe programmatically um
[snorts and clears throat] I'm not
saying ministry is not happening in
those other places but I think you guys
understand what I'm saying there's like
a non-stop nature to things um and so I
think that's a little bit of a a
misconception
um is that this uh the the front lines
nature of ministry kind of is like
always there um and that there's a lot
of people that will never come through
the doors of our church that would maybe
even call you pastor or something, you
know what I mean? Um
>> and uh uh but they've never been on a
Sunday and what do you do with that, you
know, in your in your kind of again
definitions of how do you relate to
everyone? Right? So that's one thing.
And then the third thing I'd say is um I
this is a big one for me is I long for
uh people to understand that we're we're
also
pushing and and and really trying to
make disciples just like people in the
suburbs are. But a lot of times what I
feel like people are looking to us is,
hey, let me give you a physical thing, a
tangible thing. Don't you just need this
or that? which of course is true but
like in certain ways but we're on this
long road to development and and
disciplehip you know so sort of the when
helping hurt stuff relief versus really
developing and and that's a I feel like
a big misconception is um people looking
and [clears throat] saying well don't
you just need X Y or Z and it's like
well we're on this like 30year you know
train of really trying to slowly um
disciple people which is really the same
thing you're doing it's actually a
common ground place I think for the
church but it seems used to be this
thing where it's like, oh, you're doing
something different over there. And Carl
Ellis has been super helpful for me on
this, but you know, Jesus didn't call us
to didn't go say make converts. He said
go make disciples. And the same is true
in the inner city. And it's there's a
there's certain things that make that
maybe a little tougher. Um, but we're
really trying to do the same thing. Um,
and that's a big deal for us.
>> Good word. Uh, Brad, I'm wondering how
you're hearing all this. You and I are
probably the closest to the BBS, by the
way. Are you sitting in that that cool
room we sat in in back of your house?
>> Oh man, I wish I was there with you.
It's a great room.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I really wish you hadn't
said that because that makes it a lot
harder for me to say that I feel
personally offended by everything that's
been said so far as a suburban pastor.
Um No, I'm kidding. Um, there are perks
in the suburbs, but yeah, I um yeah,
this is Yeah, this is I'm not sure how I
got to be the only uh kind of suburban
uh guy here, but um
>> I deal with a little rejection here and
there, you know. [laughter]
>> That's that's fair. Um yeah, no, this is
super interesting. I I have a I have a
strange um uh maybe a mixed perspective
in this because before we moved to
Colorado as part of a church plant in uh
downtown south city of St. Louis for six
years and part of that there for the
very beginning and um and so there's a
whole lot of ways that like man the
things you guys are talking about like
yep yep absolutely 100%. Um, and I think
one of the things that I, you know, I
didn't have any misconceptions actually
until we started this conversations. Uh,
but but now I actually have a couple and
and this is this is really good and
helpful actually because um, you know,
to the point of, you know, uh, like the
I think Jeff you said something about
like, you know, there's this kind of
misconception that the city is a dark
place. Uh I remember it was a friend of
mine who was in uh seminary uh who he he
was he's done city ministry and suburban
ministry. And I remember him saying like
Brad I figured out why I prefer uh
ministry in the city. I was like why? I
mean I can think of some reasons. It's
pretty stinking cool. Um among other
things and he said um it's easier
and and and I'm I don't I don't think
he's actually right. I think it's just
different. Right. Because I think that
the um I tell our people all the time
like do not be fooled by the the surface
level beauty of this place. There is a
lot of darkness. It's just inc and the
brokenness here is just extremely
hidden.
>> Um it's isolated and atomized down to
the individual and it's highly medicated
in ways and among people that you might
not actually understand or or or notice.
Uh but it's just as broken. it's just as
broken. The difference is um it's
actually harder to draw out because
people are not used to seeing it. They
don't know how to address it or bring it
up. And if you were the one carrying
that brokenness, it's a heck of a lot
harder to be vulnerable and open with
someone because you don't ever see any
an example of how how that happens. And
so that creates a profound loneliness uh
in the suburbs that is is is equal and
opposite to the the kind of at least in
our place uh the the more economic uh
affluence and and wealth. Um, the other
thing that's really interesting, I
think, uh, especially
in in this in my suburb anyway, the
ministry here has changed dramatically
pre versus post pandemic. Um, Axios had
an had an article um that named Boulder,
I think this was in 2023. So, it named
Boulder as having the highest per capita
number of remote uh virtual workers of
any city in the country
>> and I think it was like 38 or 40%
something some right in there and that's
wild. Um, and it includes people who are
working halfime and you know serving
tables because they're going to grad
school at CU. So it's probably even
higher percentage. And what that does is
it actually kind of flattens culture
across the board because in the internet
becomes the primary culture shaping
place for people more than a geographic
or physical place. And that just further
just kind of isolates people because
you're not interacting. And we know
because of the pandemic how much that
actually, you know, digital interaction
is not the same as inerson interaction.
And so it's just deepening that kind of
loneliness and and sense of isolation.
And so I think I mean I we could talk
about a whole lot of uh things, but I
don't want to filibuster here too much.
But um yeah, I think the the ways that
suburban ministry requires
um significant intentionality and
proactivity. Um you know, people won't
just kind of show up on Sunday morning.
They have to burn through whatever
wealth is helping them bowl with bumpers
in life first. And that is often
significant. Um, and so it takes a lot
it takes a lot for people to admit that
they actually need a savior, never mind
a church, even more than a church. Yeah,
>> Brad, I think that that's part of the
reason why I love inner city ministry
because I don't have to deal with that.
[laughter]
>> I mean, it is like Daniel said, inner
city ministry is constant. It doesn't
stop. It's it's always you're always on
to the next thing. and uh it can be very
difficult but but the transparency of
people the um that that part of it the
relationship piece I think is very
helpful and and we've had the same thing
with people wanting to stream instead
that that's not maybe so unique um
mostly because they don't have a ride
but [clears throat] um
>> but what what I've tried to emphasize
for our my congregation is um that God
has gifted them in a particular way to
build up the church and when they're not
there that doesn't happen. And so I try
to emphasize the importance of being
there to give to the church your gift
rather than
>> being there to receive. And I think that
provided for the congregation a certain
level of affirmation
that has been very helpful for people
who otherwise are not affirmed at all,
>> who often times are dismissed and
dehumanized. And so the fact that God
has gifted a person to build up the
church and the fact that that we are
very deliberate in making sure
everyone's voice is heard in the service
that I think is another piece that um
has
you know even if people aren't standing
up during our sharing time
um there's they know sharing time
happens and that is an affirmation of
the community that transfers to
individuals as well. And so, um,
>> that's fascinating because I I I just
got done telling our people like one of
the most powerful and helpful things you
can do is ask for help here
>> because if if if nobody's doing it,
nobody knows that there is a need for
their giftedness uh for for what they
have to offer and contribute either
relationally or otherwise. But also,
nobody knows how to do it because
there's nobody leading by example and
saying like the gospel is significant
enough for me that I can admit that I
need help and also um allow somebody to
to help me because that's a vulnerable
thing. Yeah.
>> You know, something I throw in there,
Brad, is that and you talked about the
uh Dan, you talked about the halves and
the have nots in Detroit. You could have
breakfast with a a homeless and and uh
dinner with a billionaire.
And uh I'd like to get his name, by the
way. Just thinking out box here, but
>> you got to get in line behind me.
>> Yeah, there you go. Uh but I think
another difference is because I'm from
Miami which is a city of suburbs really
and um and I think of where we are now
is that what you find when you peel
behind uh the the backdrop is that most
people want to appear that they belong
here including financially and many of
them are hanging on by a thread.
and and they that you don't see the
halves and the have nots as readily, but
there are halves and have nots
>> and there's some that if they lost that
one that you know five [clears throat]
hours a week, they would be they would
be in trouble whether they're in debt up
their eyeballs or whatever it might be.
So, there really are different dynamics
between the two for sure.
>> Yeah. Um I'm wondering if any of you
have any stories of collaboration where
you you saw um BBS and city come
together or or or and and to Eric's
point, however you would define where
you are and you and you um and you
figured out a way to work well together
towards uh your end and and even towards
uh those who were helping you from the
outside.
Well, I can say just in I probably
didn't make this clear enough, but the
church planting initiative that I'm
leading, the Detroit project, most of
the works are in the suburbs.
So, when we we get together every week,
we pray together. Um, deeply vested in
each other's ministries. And so, we're
there's a constant collaboration of
inner city and suburb works uh in our
network. Um, the thing that's common in
this model that I've I've tried to uh
develop and write about and and and kind
of bring to bear is that and I think
this is true just today in the
postChristian kind of culture we're
we're in is we're trying to put pastors
in areas to plant churches, get churches
going where they become known as that
community or that town or that city's
pastor.
>> And I think this goes to Eric's point.
Um we're we're finding people who
consider
our church planter their pastor
two years in and they've never stepped a
foot in his church yet.
>> They would say he's my pastor. Um, and
I'm telling you, the reason I bring that
up is because we're finding that's true
both in suburbs and city.
People want to get to know a a man of
God that they could over time begin to
trust. And then, by the way, we've also
seen many people who have started coming
to church a year, year and a half, two
years after meeting um the pastor.
>> Yeah, Dan, I would I would
[clears throat] say that that really is
true for the BBS as well. And there is
something deeply gratifying about that
in there that that someone that uh you
see whether it's at a diner or whatever
they really see you in that light and
there will be a day where even if they
don't step into your doors where they
say can you help and uh that's that's a
gift that's a privilege.
>> Yeah. I mean just real quick one other
thing you'll you guys will love this gal
that uh one of our church planters has
been working with. She owns a restaurant
bar and has a speak easy underneath her
bar. She wants nothing to do with what
his doctrine is. But when he started
promoting this thing called questioning
Christianity, which is like we're
calling a seek easy, if you will,
>> she said, the atheist said, "You know
what? Why don't you do it in my speak
easy? You can have
>> That's beautiful.
>> You can have it for free." And
[laughter]
>> wow. And so she she considers him her
pastor. And I believe there be a day
where she shows up at one of the
questioning Christianity events.
>> Good stuff. Anybody else?
>> Yeah, I would say um
I mean we owe a huge debt of gratitude
to MLAN Press.
>> We were planted by Redeemer New York and
Mlan. But MLAN, you know, all these
people that were commuting from the city
out to them and they persevered for a
couple years just to help us get this
thing started.
>> Um, and recently we begun to have
conversations about is there more? Could
we do disciplehip better and not
reinvent the wheel?
We kind ofworked across some of these
churches. they have resources
that we don't. Um, and that sort of gets
to your second question. I don't mean to
pull us too much ahead, Mike, but
>> Oh, no worries.
>> Yeah, you know, there are times where I
see friends that have planted in the
suburbs.
It, you know, their resources have
enabled them to do disciplehip in areas
where I feel like we do it weekly. what
week we e a k
you know uh and I know there's things
that we offer to them too but um
I you know I look around at some of
these churches and go wow they're really
doing that part of disciplehip better
than we have done
>> and I don't know how much of that is
contextual but some of it is some of it
is
>> great word I I I'm actually curious what
you guys think about this in the sense
of um I feel like maybe a a much more
significant kind of difference now is u
whether your context is post-Christian
uh versus a more churched context
because a lot of what you guys are
saying you know from from in larger
cities I'm like yes and amen that is
that actually has a whole lot of overlap
with my experience here in Boulder
County where you know there's about 10
churches within 20 minutes of where we
uh where we worship, but there's 150,000
people who live there and there's like
10 actual churches and and I know that
that's like a that that would be a dream
for many in uh in a highly dense urban
environment, but some of the resource
challenges you guys are talking about,
like I've actually looked to a lot of um
you know, the Redeemer uh New York guys
uh on like how do we how do we handle
being kicked out of the schools and like
not having being able to worship in a
public school like that was a m we were
we were like six weeks away from being
homeless as a church um post pandemic
and we went almost 18 months between
weekly worship because of the policies
and also available facilities here and
so like I'm just wondering if there's a
there's if that is maybe a more
significant difference than the kind of
the density and and geographic
fabric of a
anybody on that?
>> I mean, the inner city where I am is not
post-Christian. Uh, everybody everybody
believes in something, you know, and
most people believe that Jesus is Lord.
They just don't live that way, you know.
So, I mean, I can run into a guy who's
still high and drunk on the street who
can con who can quote to me all of
Isaiah,
you know, it's just amazing,
you know, content in people's heads
because they were catechized in the
black church years and years ago and
just strayed. So, a lot of it is
bringing people back to faith. where I
am, it's not a whole lot of bringing
people into the faith for the first
time. In fact, a lot of times it's,
"Yeah, I have a church." You know,
because the first question we ask is,
"Do you go to church somewhere?" And u
they say, "Yeah, I have a church. Who's
the pastor there?" is the next question
because they usually don't know.
>> They can't tell you.
>> It's a family church. And
[clears throat]
you know, they they haven't been to
church in 10, 15 years,
you know. So it's bringing people back
when they already believe mostly for me.
>> Uh do you all think that uh the um
denomination and and this isn't to uh
over glorify or bash the PCA but we are
in a denomination
and uh so many times
uh generalities can rule how we see
things. For instance, years ago uh with
church planting there was and you may
have experienced this Jeff of course you
you came out of redeemer but ba the rule
of thumb was you got support for 5 years
and you were cut off and a lot of times
that was really detrimental to the
development of the church and it made
the church planter be more about the
money than establishing a presence in
the uh in in the community. So some
adjustments had to be made in thinking.
Do you think the that the the
denomination appreciates the differences
between uh beyond the popularity of
starting something in the city between
the BBS and the city or the urban core
whatever it might be? How has the
denomination benefited you and where
could it approve?
I think though you one thing I would say
there is that you know many of the you
know our church in Harlem that what Dan
the two Dans and Eric are doing are sort
of mission outposts in some ways and
therefore churches being committed to
them as unique mission outposts is
critical. Redeemer was wonderful about
that as were a number of churches in our
area. They were glad to support the work
in Harlem for years and uh I'm I'm
profoundly grateful for that. that I
think they understood that I was I I at
least had that privilege of them
understanding that because there are
different churches being planted in you
know redeemer could not be any more
different from the church I did in
Harlem. Uh and uh they you know required
yeah different understandings of how
they're going to thrive in over the
years.
>> So it helped for Redeemer and for Tim to
respect the reality of those differences
that were needed too.
Yeah, hugely. Um, and on a on a whole
bunch of different fronts, but yeah, for
sure.
>> Very good. Anybody else?
>> Yeah, I mean I just part again part of
this model that I've developed um we're
encouraging church planters and this
reason I call it missionary model or
city campus model.
>> We're encouraging church planters to
raise money almost in perpetuity. M
[clears throat]
>> um the whole three to five years of
funding I mean you go back to Al Bar was
adamant that it's no more than three
years
>> you know and he's changing his tune
there. else saying no it's a different
it's a different game now but you know
Ted Powers will say today 7 to 10 years
>> I'm just saying for the time being this
is why I love crew guys who are coming
in and becoming church planters because
they're used to raising money in
perpetuity
>> and I think that's what needs to happen
to give you the capacity to do the
ministry you really want to do and I
think church planters especially do
default to reshuffleling sheep because
they're running out of money
Right.
>> I mean, that's the biggest challenge,
one of the biggest challenges that I
have is I think our accounts are down to
about 35 grand right now.
>> So, [clears throat]
that's my margin. Um, we spend or our
budget for Mercy Ministry is about 2,000
a month. So that becomes difficult to
maintain and that is a big part of our
illustrating the gospel. So when I bring
the gospel to somebody,
I need to be able to demonstrate to that
person
my love for you is more than just
spiritual. It's also physical. I, you
know, I don't want to be agnostic about
salvation. You know, salvation is also
physical sometimes. And and so when
Christ brings salvation, when he brings
healing in a physical way, that's the
illustration of the spiritual healing
that we all need ultimately. And when I
can't do that well, then it
[clears throat] it tends to build hard
feelings and,
you know, lost expectations that I can
deal with that, but it's makes it
difficult to try to navigate how to
communicate to somebody who's used to
entitlements and who has received, you
know, gifts of mercy for bus pass or for
heat or for whatever it happens to be,
you know, helping to finish the rent.
Um, and you know when that ends or when
that when I can't afford to
provide that, it can be difficult
sometimes.
So that support is important. The the
the support from like work
particularized for six five years now. I
will always need to raise money. Always.
>> Yeah. I think a helpful thing along
those lines was um
I love that Mother Teresa line where she
says, you know, we need the poor more
than the poor need us. And therefore
having to and actually it's not just a
nice romantic emotionally thing to say.
There's there's once you parse that out
and you can communicate that to uh some
of the wealthier congregations around
you, they can understand, oh yeah, this
is actually really important for us.
We're not just uh coming alongside and
helping this poor struggling church.
We're in this mission together of seeing
the kingdom and the new creation witness
to and uh these guys are on the front
lines of some of that really important
kingdom new creation witness if we you
know trying to help our our suburban um
brothers and sisters understand that
which in my experience they were more
than glad to to understand there was not
a reticence to that but still there is
that that work that needs to be done but
Yeah, I think works like the two Danes
and Erics uh will always need uh
meaningful support and Redeemer tries to
do that with any number of urban
ministries.
>> I'm curious to hear from Eric as to
where about your funding, Eric.
Um I'm assuming from what you said that
you're thinking more perpetual.
>> Oh, for sure. Yeah. So yeah, my I mean
our collaboration experience was you
know we have a church here in Orlando
called New City um and that's the church
that uh sent us out uh started there as
an intern. So, you know, I think
building a relationship uh with a a
church prior to, you know, going out, so
to speak, it was was very beneficial for
us. Um because I think they were they
they've been extremely patient. Um
similar to Redeemer, just kind of
continuing to walk us walk this out with
us. Um continue to support us today. Um,
and yet now our budget is, you know, far
different, far, you know, than it was 12
years ago. And so the the funding now
is, um, you know, it's one of my primary
jobs. Now I'm a little bit different, I
think, in this group in that I'm not
goes back to what I said earlier. The
community knows me as Pastor E, but I
don't have don't have a Sunday morning
thing right now. Um and I've also I
think one of the biggest things that was
again personal story for me but I trying
to understand who we each are as leaders
and how we work I think is one thing the
denomination
they honestly I don't know that they
quite know how to do that part because
there tends to be a
like [clears throat] a this is what it
means to be a church planter type of
thing and clearly we're all different.
Um but then sometimes we try to like be
that thing and that doesn't work very
well. One of the help most helpful
things for me has been learning who I am
um quite honestly as a leader. And so
part of the the to answer your question
about funding is just we've
my one of my main jobs now has been
fundraising for the entire ministry
which has after school program now a
school mental health counseling. We're
endeavoring to have vocational training
sort of building out this environment.
But the what I learned is that I cannot
do this alone obviously, but if I spend
more time working on the vision and
fundraising and then being able to hire
people who actually do some of the work,
you know, on the ground a little better
than me, uh, it goes a lot better. Um,
but I spent a lot of my ministry in a
lot of shame feeling like I had to do
both.
>> Like trying to be this fundraiser but
then also trying to do the work on the
ground. And the the reality is it I mean
fundraising is a full-time thing in a
lot of ways.
So
>> Glenn Oh, sorry. Sorry, Eric.
>> That's really helpful to hear.
>> Glenn, you were getting [clears throat]
Yeah. I had a I had a question for you
all that are working in underresourced
areas and maybe you'd expect that this
coming from me because of where I'm
located but with the change in
administration and politics [snorts]
um do you anticipate
that
the demographic of the PCA which is more
sympathetic
with the changes to be less generous or
more suspicious about giving to the poor
giving to poor work. So you know what
I'm does that make sense that question
there is right I've had people out of
work because
US aid and this idea of giving has been
cut. So I'm wondering if that's going to
impact some of the churches that give to
you.
I think giving is so much about
relationship. Um, and that's what it
goes back to the thing I just said
earlier, which is you have to at some
point realize like, man, like I can't do
this alone.
>> And that was one of the biggest gifts
God gave me was stop doing this alone.
Like um uh it's just one of the worst
things. So I I think um
I don't I don't want to say like
absolutely not there's no effect. That
would be crazy for me to say that. Um
but I I think when
one of the again one of the realizing
for me is is a lot of times I feel like
uh I'm this bridge between two worlds in
a lot of ways. So I have people who have
no idea what the inner city is like and
like to and tell me they but act like
they do, right? Or think they know all
the answers. So and then I've got the
inner city and they don't know what's
going on over here. And I'm kind of like
doing this thing where I'm trying to
like navigate that relationships. But I
but recognizing again that I have a
ministry to the to use Dan's the
billionaire although I haven't met one
of those yet. I don't think so. I mean
that connects here. But um but there's a
ministry there. Uh and recognizing this
guy isn't or or woman is not just a a
dollar sign but but needs this to what
uh Jeff you were saying they need this
or this interchange needs to happen. Um
and as much of a mystery over there. So
I don't know that administration of
course it matters in certain ways but
the the relationship I have with people
I think I want to say um probably the
thing that matters more and all that if
that answers your question but
>> Eric that is extremely helpful to me um
I' I've I've neglected fundraising
because the workload of trying to do
everything is so difficult. Um we've
been we people have been very generous
with us. We received $200,000 to buy a
church and parsonage and we're mortgage
free on it. So, what a blessing that is.
And then another church in Madison gave
us $90,000, which I should pay back, but
they said, "Look, if you can't, then
don't." Uh, to put on new siding and a
new roof that we needed. So, so the
people have been very generous with the
my favorite word, one of my favorite
words in scripture is the word
sunerggoy. And it's it's the it's it's
translated fellow worker co-orker that
Paul uses directly in in connection with
giving.
When somebody gives friend of sinner's
church,
they're in the field with us.
>> They're a fellow worker with us. And
sometimes I think folks in the suburbs
are thinking, "What can I do? I need to
do something. I need to be there. I need
to. But you are, you know, people are
with us when they have given. They're a
fellow worker. They're in the field with
us. And and I think I think a light went
on, Eric, when you were talking about
that for me because I'm 64. I'm going to
be transitioning out. somebody else is
going to be coming in and I need to make
sure somehow, you know, the idea of
doing fundraising full-time and giving
the pastoral and and mercy work to
others that I raise money to support.
I think that's something maybe maybe
that's so obvious I should just uh slap
myself on the back of the head for not
thinking it through. But um but that
that is a transformative thought that I
haven't had before.
>> Dan, um thank you and thank you for
translating that word. It's the only
word in the Greek New Testament I hadn't
memorized and I appreciate that.
[laughter]